Chao Zhang

Zhejiang University, China Hangzhou, Zhejiang 310058, China zhangchaohci@gmail.com https://zhangchaodesign.com/

Research Interests

Digital Youth: Designing interactive technologies to scaffold children in creating, learning, and understanding the world, e.g., AI-fused learning technologies, creativity support tools for children.

Human-AI Collaboration: Exploring human-AI collaborative approaches to augment human capabilities of cognition (e.g., creativity, engagement), perception (e.g., observation), and action (e.g., design).

User Experience: Investigating ethical issues (e.g., dark patterns) and intervention techniques in user experience design to empower end users in regaining autonomy from malicious technologies.

Education

Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China

09/2020 - 03/2023 (expc.)

M.E. in Industrial Design Engineering

GPA: 95.15/100.00, 1/60, Advisor: Cheng Yao

Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China

09/2016 - 07/2020

B.E. in Electrical Engineering, minor in Digital Media Technology

GPA: 3.83/4.00, 3/77

Publication

Peer-Reviewed Conference and Journal Papers

- C.1. **Chao Zhang**, Cheng Yao, Jiayi Wu, Weijia Lin, Lijuan Liu, Ge Yan, and Fangtian Ying. 2022. Story-Drawer: A Child-AI Collaborative Drawing System to Support Children's Creative Visual Storytelling. In *Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '22).* [PDF]
- C.2. Ge Yan, Cheng Yao, **Chao Zhang**, Jiadi Wang, Yuqi Hu, and Fangtian Ying. 2022. MusicCollage: A Music Composition Tool for Children Based on Synesthesia and a Genetic Algorithm. In *Proceedings of the 2022 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (HCII '22)*. [PDF]
- J.2. Yang Chen, Katherine Fennedy, Anna Fogel, Shengdong Zhao, **Chao Zhang**, Lijuan Liu, and Chingchiuan Yen. 2022. SSpoon: A Shape-changing Spoon That Optimizes Bite Size for Eating Rate Regulation. *ACM Journal on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies*. 6, 3, 105:1-105:32. [PDF]
- J.1. Lijuan Liu, Jiahao Guo, **Chao Zhang**, Zhangzhi Wang, Pinqi Zhu, Tuo Fang, Junwu Wang, Cheng Yao, and Fangtian Ying. 2021. ElectroPaper: Design and Fabrication of Paper-Based Electronic Interfaces for the Water Environment. *Electronics*. 10, 5, 604. [PDF]

Under Review Manuscripts

M.3. Anonymous Authors (As the **1st author**). 2023. Designing an AI-fused Tool that Supports Children in Observational Drawing and Promotes their Connectedness to Nature [Title modified to ensure blind review]. *Submitted to CHI '23*

- M.2. Anonymous Authors (As the **co-1st author**). 2023. Design Transparency and End-User Interventions for Dark Patterns [Title modified to ensure blind review]. *Submitted to CHI '23*
- M.1. Anonymous Authors (As the **2nd author**). 2023. Understanding seekers' engagement with received feedback in online critique communities [Title modified to ensure blind review]. *Submitted to CHI '23*

Posters, Extended Abstracts, and Workshop Papers

- EA.4. Ge Yan, **Chao Zhang**, Jiadi Wang, Zheng Xu, Jianhui Liu, Jintao Nie, Fangtian Ying, and Cheng Yao. 2022. CamFi: An AI-driven and Camera-based System for Assisting Users in Finding Lost Objects in Multi-Person Scenarios. In *Extended Abstracts of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '22*). [PDF]
- EA.3. **Chao Zhang**, Zili Zhou, Jiayi Wu, Yajing Hu, Yaping Shao, Jianhui Liu, Yuqi Hu, Fangtian Ying, and Cheng Yao. 2021. Bio Sketchbook: An AI-assisted Sketching Partner for Children's Biodiversity Observational Learning. In *Extended Abstracts of the 2021 ACM Interaction Design and Children Conference (IDC EA '21).* [PDF]
- EA.2. **Chao Zhang**, Cheng Yao, Jianhui Liu, Zili Zhou, Weilin Zhang, Lijuan Liu, Fangtian Ying, Yijun Zhao, and Guanyun Wang. 2021. StoryDrawer: A Co-Creative Agent Supporting Children's Storytelling through Collaborative Drawing. In *Extended Abstracts of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '21)*. [PDF]
- EA.1. Muling Huang, Lingyan Zhang, Lijuan Liu, Pinqi Zhu, **Chao Zhang**, Pitchayapat Sonchaeng, Weiqiang Ying, Pinhao Wang, Yuqi Hu, Fangtian Ying, and Cheng Yao. 2021. ColorGuardian: Customize Skin Tattoos for Children with Vitiligo. In *Extended Abstracts of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '21).* [PDF]

Research Experience

SaNDwich Lab, University of Notre Dame (ND), USA

06/2022 - Present

Advisors: Prof. Toby Jia-jun Li and Prof. Yaxing Yao (University of Maryland, Baltimore County)

• Proposed a bottom-up end-user-empowerment approach to address dark patterns in UX; conceptualized such an approach into a technology probe based on protection motivation theory; developed a browser extension for "fixing" dark patterns through a malleable interface approach; designed protocols for a two-phase co-design study; qualitatively analyzed collected data to explore users' underlying needs, preferences, and challenges related to the intervention of UX dark patterns. [M.2.]

HCI Lab, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST), China 06/2022 - 09/2022 Advisor: Prof. Xiaojuan Ma

Used pattern.en and NLTK to characterize 287,000 collected comments in online critique communities
(OCCs) with content-based features (i.e., actionability, justification, specificity, and valence); developed
a coding scheme to characterize OCCs seekers' cognitive engagement; constructed two ground-truth
datasets and implemented machine learning models (e.g., SVC, MLP, RF, etc.) to classify seekers' cognitive engagement and artifacts' creation stages (WIP or complete); [M.3.]

INNO Lab, Zhejiang University (ZJU), China

07/2020 - Present

Advisors: Prof. Cheng Yao and Prof. Fangtian Ying

• Conducted a formative investigation to identify the challenges children face in visual storytelling; iteratively designed and built a creativity support tool to scaffold 6-10-year-old children in visual storytelling through child-AI collaboration; proposed one user-initiative and one AI-initiative collaborative strategies; conducted a 2 × 2 between-subject user study with 64 participants to quantitatively and qualitatively examine the efficacy of the two proposed strategies. [EA.2.] [C.1.]

- Conducted observational studies and interviews with children to understand their needs in nature-based observational drawing; designed and built an AI-fused system, leveraging generative models, recognition models, and mobile technologies, to support children's observational drawing of plants and promote their connectedness to nature; Using mixed methods to conduct a within-subject in-situ user study with 22 participants to evaluate the efficacy of our system. [EA.3.] [M.1.]
- Used Grasshopper to develop a computational design tool based on Rhino3D software for designers to design waterproof paper-based electronic prototypes working in water environments; Using Arduino, Raspberry Pi, and our paper-based electronic interfaces to build 5 hardware applications that can illuminate underwater, detect water quality, float adaptively with water temperature, rotate to capture underwater scenes, and morph with the human touch. [J.2.]

Selected Design Awards and Exhibitions

A.4.	Iron Award, A' Design Award, Italy. [Link]	2022
A.3.	iF Talent Award, iF Design Award, Germany. [Link]	2021
A.2.	Honorable Mention, Design Intelligence Award (DIA), China. [Link]	2021
A.1.	Outstanding Winner, China Graduate AI Innovation Competition, China.	2021
E.2.	China Design Exhibition, China.	2022
E.1.	Global Grad Show, Dubai Design Week, The United Arab Emirates, [Link,1] [Link,2]	2021

Selected Honors and Scholarships

H.2.	Valedictorian, School of IOT, Jiangnan University, China.	2020
H.1.	Jiangnan Talent (Only 10 awardees in Jiangnan University), Jiangnan University, China.	2019
S.2.	National Scholarship (Top 1% in Zhejiang University), Ministry of Education, China.	2021
S.1.	National Scholarship (Top 1% in Jiangnan University), Ministry of Education, China.	2018

Skills

Language: Native Mandarin, Fluent English (IELTS 7.0)

Research: Interview, Survey, Participatory Design, Design Probe, Thematic Analysis, etc.

Design: User Experience Design (Figma, Sketch, etc.), 3D Modelling and Rendering (Cinema 4D, Corona Render, Rhino 3D, etc.), Computational Design (P5.js, Processing, Grasshopper, etc.), Graphic Design (Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, etc.)

Computing: Front-End Development (Javascript, HTML, CSS, Vue.js, etc.), Data Analysis (Matplotlib, Numpy, Pandas, SPSS, JASP, etc.), and Machine Learning (Sklearn, PyTorch, Tensorflow, etc.)

Prototyping: 3D Printing, Laser Cutting, Fabrication and Hardware Assembly, Basic Circuit Design, etc.

References

Prof. Xiaojuan Ma, Associate Professor, HKUST
Prof. Toby Jia-jun Li, Assistant Professor, ND
Prof. Yaxing Yao, Assistant Professor, UMBC

mxj@cse.ust.hk toby.j.li@nd.edu yaxingyao@umbc.edu